<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pithie, and most earnest exhortation, concerning the estate of Christiandome together with the meanes to preserue and defend the same; dedicated to al christian kings princes and potentates, with all other the estates of Christiandome: by a Germaine gentleman, a louer of his countrey.</title>
            <title>Ad potentissimos ac serenissimos reges commonefactio. English</title>
            <author>Marnix van St. Aldegonde, Philips van, 1538-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17450.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843509</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8248</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8248)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 315:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pithie, and most earnest exhortation, concerning the estate of Christiandome together with the meanes to preserue and defend the same; dedicated to al christian kings princes and potentates, with all other the estates of Christiandome: by a Germaine gentleman, a louer of his countrey.</title>
                  <title>Ad potentissimos ac serenissimos reges commonefactio. English</title>
                  <author>Marnix van St. Aldegonde, Philips van, 1538-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Waldegrave],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Antwerpe [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno D. 1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Germaine gentleman = Philips van Marnix van St. Aldegonde.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Ad potentissimos ac serenissimos reges .. commonefactio.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed at London by R. Waldegrave (STC).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5147 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8248:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8248:1"/>
            <p>A pithie, And moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt exhortation, concerning the eſtate of Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, together with the meanes to preſerue and defend the ſame;</p>
            <p>DEDICATED To al chriſtian Kings Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Potentates, with all other the eſtates of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiandome:</p>
            <p>By a Germaine Gentleman, a louer of his Countrey.</p>
            <p>Printed at Antwerpe. ANNO D. 1583.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8248:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8248:2"/>
            <head>To all Chriſtian Kinges, <hi>Princes and</hi> Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, with all other the <hi>eſtates of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we would in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of vnderſtanding weye and ponder what ſoeuer the councels &amp; actions which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue in other mens af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and buſines, we ſhould no dout builde the whole eſtate of our life vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a more aſſured foundation, &amp; with al eſchue an infinite number of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities aſwell publique as perticuler which now we do incurre. For the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of other mens perils and loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, being the moſte faithfull teachers and expert guids of this preſent life, would make vs more warie and ſtand vs in ſtead of a rule whereby to direct al our enterpriſes, determinations, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct of al our affairs. This kind of wiſedome haue the moſte circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8248:3"/>in all ages, accounted to be, not onely of the greateſt profite, but alſo moſt milde and tollerable, and which doth yeelde greateſt contentation to the practitioners of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Howbeit it happeneth for the moſt part, that in the gouernm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>et &amp; directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our affaires we be ſo altered, either with hope, or feare, or ſome other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty or infirmity, that we can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend or forſee the miſchief which eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at hand hangeth ouer our heads, vntil it hath vtterly ſnared and caught vs through ſome ſudden &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loked for fall &amp; ruine, and ſo we doe fully ſuffer the puniſhment due to our dulnes &amp; negligence: Whereby not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we do many times wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into the conſideration of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens affairs, yet in caſe our ſelues be to eſchue the like perilles, it falleth ordinarily out, that either in pondring the waightines of the matter, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed with doubt of the vncertain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent therof, either waiting that others firſt ſet to their handes, either hoping time enough to be able to prouide therfore, we do ſo prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our buſines
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8248:3"/>that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcaping vs, al this goodly wiſdome, and wary forecaſt that we had conceiued in the conſideration of the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of other mens miſcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, vaniſheth into ſmoke &amp; ſo ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wereth away, that weca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not thereof reape any fruit or commodity.</p>
            <p>Hitherto was there neuer prouince, Towne, or valeant &amp; vertuous citizen, but did account their ſafety, libertye &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon quiet to depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derat &amp; peaceable gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their mightieſt borderers: as alſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing went ſo nere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or was of ſuch importance, as their neighbors to eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliſh their eſtate in iuſtice, or moderat affection, &amp; in peaceable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues within their owne bounds &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, as it were within certaine ſtrong bulwarks &amp; barriers. And aſſuredly as ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is euer to be feared &amp; ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all maner of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo is it moſt dangerous in thoſe, who being alredy of great power &amp; ſtrength, cannot ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe bridle their couetous aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, how large ſoeuer the extent of their boundes &amp; limites be: For ſith it is vnpoſſible that any innouations,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8248:4"/>or alterations in kingdomes and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealths, can hapen without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting, moleſting or general confoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of al things, it muſt neceſſarily fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low that not only the bordering pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, but alſo thoſe countries which lie farther off, being toſſed &amp; turmoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the waues &amp; billowes of ſuch their neighbours ambition, ſhal final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee entangled and ſwallowed vp in the gulfe of ſo horrible calamitie.</p>
            <p>For as the waues of the Ocean Sea, being toſſed with ſome mighty ſtorm &amp; ſo ſwelling out of their banks &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary limittes, may at the firſt with ſmal labor be reſtrained through ſome ſtrong wall ſpeedily erected &amp; by the diligence of al the neighbours &amp; bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, each helping other in ſo great peril, oppoſed againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but hauing once pierced &amp; made breach in a bank or two, &amp; therby diſpearſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; ſlowing ouer the whole champion country without reſtreint, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not after ward either by power or policie be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, or ſtopped from breeding and working ineſtimable &amp; ineuitable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8248:4"/>among both men &amp; cattell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting the ſaide Countrye, but alſo oftentimes againſt whole towns, coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries and Kingdoms lying further off: Euen ſo likewiſe ambitious Princes endeuouring to enlarge their owne boundes and limits, although with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens loſſes, may eaſily in the beginning of their enterpriſes bee repreſſed, and by a common conſent and correſpondence of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, generallye oppoſinge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt their attempts, be ſo reſtreined within their own bounds and limittes, that hardlye they ſhall put any to loſſe or other notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience: but hauing once paſſed their armies into other mens prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and beeing allured by the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of taking ſome ſtrong holde or place of importance, and ſo concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome hope of further extending the boundes of their empire: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially knowing their name to bee growne terrible amongſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, there is then no meanes, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or force how great ſo euer, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8248:5"/>other let, that can ſtop the forcible courſe of their madde affection and franticke ambition, coueting to rule and command ouer others. This mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſoeuer among the wiſeſt haue heretofore conſidered (as all thoſe haue done, which thought it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to vſe diſcreet moderation in the conduct of their affaires) haue euer holden this for a principle, namely that it is the duety of euerye good countriman, eſpecially of Kings, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and gouernours, not onely dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and in time to ſee that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of their Countryes, people and prouinces be in good eſtate, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and peaceably ordered, but alſo to preuent ſuch Princes and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures as are prouoked by ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and allured with deſire of rule, from tranſporting any power, vnder whatſoeuer colour and pretence, into other mens dominions, alſo from all ambitious enlargeing of their own bounds &amp; limits.</p>
            <p>Vpon this grounde did the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſeeking euen in the beginning to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8248:5"/>the power of the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> and to ſet <hi>Spayne</hi> free from the <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> bondage, thinke it neceſſary to aide the <hi>Mamertynes</hi> whom they had beſieged.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe when <hi>Antiochus</hi> the noble, vnder title of the protectorſhip of his nephew, ſought to ſeaze vppon <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Romans</hi> commaunded him to deſiſt, &amp; content himſelf with the poſſesſion of his predeceſſors an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient dominions: and that generally they neuer ſuffred any prince or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth whatſoeuer to riſe into too great power.</p>
            <p>Hereupon alſo the <hi>Venetians</hi> both now and aforetime obtayned the name of wiſdome &amp; ſinguler forecaſt. For as they were neuer eaſily induced to new warres, ſo haue they alwais ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in ſuch manner tempered their determinations and counſailes, that if any neighbour, either prince or common wealth, through immoderat deſire of gouernment, areared warre agaynſt his borderers, their armies were ſtill in readineſſe as a helpe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8248:6"/>and ſafegard to the weaker party, to the end that thus reſtraining the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Italian Princes &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths in equall balance, they might kepe them from all hope of ſubduing them by force of armes, which perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall reſolution of theirs is among all other excellent matters noted to bee the moſt certaine reaſon, whereby we ſee their common wealth not onely to haue flouriſhed and proſpered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d years, but alſo in al ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue &amp; wiſdome to be growne into ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration among other nations. This was that Maxime which <hi>Laurence de Medicis,</hi> the wiſeſt man in his time in <hi>Italie,</hi> did ſo earneſtly and with ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular endeuour all his life time both followe and maintaine, vnto whome that great quietneſſe and tranquility which ſo long as he liued all <hi>Italie</hi> did enioy, was in the opinion of moſt hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographers attributed: For he ſo brideled the affections of the Italian Princes and ſouerainties, partly by councell and aduice, and partly by the power and authority of the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8248:6"/>common wealth, wherof himſelfe was chiefe gouernour, that if any, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly pasſing his boundes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits did enterpriſe ought againſt his neighbour, he was immediatly redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into his duety by the mutuall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of other Princes and people vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, there is no wiſe man but ſeeth, knoweth, and is fully reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, yea, and grieuouſly accuſeth that people, tearming them traytours to their Country, who eyther daunted with feare and cowardlineſſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked with deſire of reſt and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, either drowned in retchleſneſſe, or deteined in ciuill diſſentions, haue ſo ſuffered their ambitious neighbors empire to encreaſe, that afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnable to bear the brunt or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the power and might thereof, they haue beene forced with their owne eyes to ſee themſelues ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and their Country reduced into extreame miſery and calamity. Yea, who is there among vs, that is not of opinion that the ancient <hi>Gaules</hi> might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8248:7"/>haue liued in liberty &amp; bin exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Romans</hi> bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, if by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent they had altogether with ſtoode the power of <hi>Iulius Caeſar?</hi> But ſome ſtanding as idle lookers vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their neighbors, &amp; other with their owne weapons encreaſing the power of the <hi>Romaynes,</hi> thinges grew in ſhort ſpace to that extremitie that the ſo mighty &amp; large empire of the <hi>Gaules</hi> was in the ende reſtrained into a <hi>Roman</hi> prouince, &amp; vtterlyouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in moſt vile bondage.</p>
            <p>Howe haue the <hi>Italians</hi> themſeleues ſped? If at the beginning they had with a common power and army ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the riſing of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and not ſuffered the <hi>Antiates, Crustumniens, Centans</hi> and <hi>Latins</hi> each one ſeuerally, alſo ſoon after the <hi>Volſques, Aeques, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins,</hi> &amp; then the <hi>Samnites, Vmbres, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Hetrurians,</hi> and other people by little and little one after another to haue ſtouped vnder their yoake: had they not firſt preſerued their owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and then freed al other nations in <hi>Europe</hi> from that infamous bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage wherunto they afterward fel? and yet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8248:7"/>did there not in manner any of them reap any benefit of al theſe examples: For notwithſtanding they well weyed other mens caſes, yet was there none that coulde accomodate the fruite of ſuch conſideration to him ſelfe or his own time. So that after <hi>Italie,</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atly <hi>Cicil,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Affrica,</hi> &amp; within a while al <hi>Aſia,</hi> &amp; finally in a manner the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal worlde being come vnder the power of the <hi>Romans,</hi> felt the burden of their folly. Through the like giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; negligence, wherin the harts of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kings &amp; princes haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bene drowned, the <hi>Saraſens</hi> haue found oportunity &amp; means moſt villa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouſly to entrap &amp; entangle the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt churches of <hi>Aſia, Affrica</hi> &amp; <hi>Aegypt,</hi> vnder the lamentable yoke &amp; bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> through the which they bee vtterly alienated from the true knoweledge of the Heauenlye Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: whoſe ſuccesſion and tiranny, the cruell Empire of the <hi>Ottomanns,</hi> which tooke their beeginning of ſo conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible an ofspring &amp; is now (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a trice) enhanced to ſuch might, as it haue penetrated not onely into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8248:8"/>the dominions of <hi>Aſia</hi> &amp; <hi>Affrica,</hi> but alſo haue ſubuerted, ouerthrown and turned topſy turuy euen the inwarde Prouinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> haue ſeazed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea it is euident to all men that moſt Chriſtian kings and nations being ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſied in their owne ciuil warres &amp; domeſtical diſſentions, either daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with daſtardlineſſe, or ſwelling in ambition, little weening their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours loſſes to be in ought preiudicial vnto their eſtates, and each one ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſuppoſing himſelfe to haue of his own, power ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to turn the ſtorm from him and his dominions, haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the <hi>Turkes</hi> more leiſure &amp; opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to execute their cruell deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations then them ſelues durſte haue deſired, or ſo much as once haue hoped for. So that had not the pollicy power of <hi>Germany</hi> withſtoode their flame, and thought it expedient, by an Emperial decree, with the coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their whole forces, coine &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique reuenues to preuent theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges of the <hi>Ottomanus,</hi> long ſince had the whole Empire of Chirſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8248:8"/>bene ſubuerted and wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into aſhes: yea the very power &amp; ſtrength of <hi>Germany</hi> was it which alone heretofore withſtoode the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> armies: For when all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> together with the inhabitants of <hi>Affrica</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> vnto the very <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> had vniuerſally thorough their aforeſaid ſlouth accepted the yoke of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, the <hi>Germaines</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſſembling their whole forces togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſundry times conquered and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrewe their whole power, &amp; ſome times winning, ſometimes looſing did ſtill ſo ſupply their armies, that the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil warres enſuing in the <hi>Romane</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, they with great force and in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places, made diuers and notable roades &amp; inuaſions into the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, &amp; finally gathered ſuch courage that they taught thoſe, who before were inured in conqueſtes and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, now not only to receiue the yoke of the <hi>Germane</hi> Empire, but alſo did vtterly ſubuert and in manner roote them out, which their ſo valiaunt vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories &amp; noble valure can not by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8248:9"/>poſterity be ſufficiently extolled and commended.</p>
            <p>Howbeit the more valiant and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious that our predeceſſours haue bene: the more maruelous, &amp; among al honorable perſons lamentable may it be, that thus degenerating from the auncient valeantiſe &amp; victorious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of our forefathers, we do peceably beholde and quietly ſuffer the cruell and proud yoke of the Spaniſh tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (already extended almoſt ouer the whole worlde) thus leyſurely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croche vpon vs, to the end for euer to ſubuert both vs and our poſterity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>I wil not by compariſons of nations and Princes one with an other, make any name more odious then other (for al kind of ſeruitude is heauy and intollerable, and vtterly vnworthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that beareth the face of a man) but I doubt whether the yoke of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> nation, (drawing their petigree from the <hi>Moores</hi> and <hi>Saraſens,</hi> and of late through force and rigour of the inquiſition forced vnwillingly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8248:9"/>Chriſtian Religion) be any whit more tolerable then the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: Of my ſelfe I will affirme no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, onely I referre the iudgement thereof to the inhabitants of <hi>Granado,</hi> the <hi>Indians, Neopolitains</hi> and others: notwithſtanding vndoutedly the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> yoke, although it were through the greedy coueteouſnes of both Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and ſouldiours (who are ſaide to haue deſtroyed more confederate Cities with their gariſons, then ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies townes with their armies) intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to all men: yet beeing compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the pride, cruelty, and oue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> may by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſundry moſt excellent vertues, wherewith it was endewed, be both termed, and accounted in liew of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, liberty, and in ſtead of a forced obedience, a iuſt and lawful commandement: but howſoeuer that caſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth al the world doth plainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, that vnleſſe in time it be looked vnto, and by ſome general conſent and vnion of the counſail and force of al other Kings &amp; princes, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:8248:10"/>purpoſes be preuented and ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it wil ſhortly ſo come to paſſe that their ſtrength being growne to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thorough the common negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and want of conſideration in all, thoſe men ſhall ouer late begin to reſiſt him, which now at pleaſure and eaſe beholding the fire conſuming the lowe countries, doe not thinke that the flame thereof doeth anye whit touch them, either conſider that through their owe ſlouth and ſimple forecaſt, the coales of Spaniſhe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition will in ſhorte ſpace ſo kindle and take holde, that they will reduce both their owne territories, and the dominions of al other ſtates and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into aſhes.</p>
            <p>Neither are they to ſuppoſe that this Fire of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ambition is to bee termined with the Prouinces of <hi>Barbant, Holand,</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> ſith that already not onely the flakes and ſparckles, but alſo the very firy flames thereof are flowen into <hi>Italy, France, England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Germanie:</hi> Yea and haue taken holde of almoſt al the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8248:10"/>habitable lande. And which is more, euen the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelues do not forbeare to rereporte that by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine celeſtiall conſtitution, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie of the whole worlde is due vnto them, hauing as an earneſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof, through their owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might, conquered a new world to our aunceſters heretofore vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, which they haue beautified with lawes and cuſtomes, poliſhed with maners and diſcipline, and indued, and inſtructed in the Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique religion: thinking it to be their bounden duetie: alſo that they ought, hauing eſtabliſhed their Monarchie, to endeuour them ſelues to force all other people, and nations vnto their Religion and diſcipline, and thorough the onely terrour of their armies, and power of their Empire, to determine all controuerſies in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; cauſes concerning Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges doe they not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dayly in familiar ſpeech giue out: but alſo in deedes, whiche are the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8248:11"/>aſſured tokens, and in al their actions, counſails and enterpiſes, aſwel paſt as preſent, confirme: for their onely ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the marke wherat they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually leuel, is, how they may, when they haue ſubdued the low countries, in the middeſt of the ſame eſtabliſh an ordinary reſorte for the warres, from whence they may at al times at their pleaſure and eaſe paſſe their armies in to <hi>England, France,</hi> or <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſo firſt with al rigour to entreate theſe whom they haue found moſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their enterpriſes, and afterward to preſcribe vnto all other Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and nations, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal come in their heads, and thus excluding each from al help of other, and compaſſing them with their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to reduce vnder their yoke all thoſe which willingly wil not yeelde vnto them al ready and perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>This is the marke whereat they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies haue ſhot. To this ende haue al their counſailes, practiſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes tended, as appeareth in that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8248:11"/>with their armies oppreſſed <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> they ſence not only extended their power into <hi>Germanie</hi> vnder colour of reſtoring religion, but alſo haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to ſubdue the whole eſtate and monarchie of Chriſtiandome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſubiection.</p>
            <p>And that I may the more plainely open this matter vnto you, moſte mighty Kinges, Princes, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. It is expedient orderly to ſet downe a briefe and manifeſt diſcourſe of all the counſayles, dealinges and practiſes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> euen from the original of their enterpriſes vnto this time, to the end their purpoſes, driftes and deuiſes beeing detected and layde open to the whole worlde, we may in time apply and miniſter al conuenient and meete medicines to that miſchiefe, which is ſo knowen to the whole chriſtian common wealth. Wherein I will not vndoubtedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe any thing, but that which haue bene done in the face of the whole worlde, and as it were, in ſo publique a theatre, that no man can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8248:12"/>thereof, which thing whileſt I do diſcourſe and ſet before your eyes, I beſeech you (noble Princes) vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to be attentiue, and turning your affections from all opinions preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially conceaued, diligently to apply your mindes to conſider, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the aſſured and liuely truth of the whole affaires.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniarde</hi> therefore, through the valiauncy of King <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of the bondage of the <hi>Moores,</hi> and by continuall exerciſe in Warres, growne ſo perfect and ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in armes, that he had conceiued a certaine opinion of himſelfe, that he had either ſurmounted all other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in warlike knowledge and fame, or at the leaſt boorded the moſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, did immediatly caſt his view vpon <hi>Italy,</hi> and in his heart deuiſed to attempt to ſubdue the ſame to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, being thereunto eſpecially moued, and allured by reaſon of the great plenty, and aboundance of all thinges in the ſaide Countrie, which they had found and tried at ſuch time
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8248:12"/>as the <hi>Arragons</hi> (by nation <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and then ruling in <hi>Naples</hi>) had cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their helpe againſt the French ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: they had before encroched vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>French</hi> the Ile of <hi>Sicil,</hi> being a very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious place for paſſage of their munition, armyes, &amp; ſouldiours, and very conuenient for the prouiſion of whatſoeuer were requiſite &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry either to the making of warre, or relieuing the wantes of their men.</p>
            <p>Giuing ouer therefore the defence of the poſterity of <hi>Alfonce,</hi> who had craued their helpe, they entred com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of accord with the <hi>French</hi> and ſo agreed to part betweene them al that prouince. But perceiuing the <hi>French</hi> to be ſlacke in their buſines &amp; ſlow in proſecuting this warre: taking occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie ariſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their bounds, they renued the warres againſt them with all extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and yet ſo, that ſhortly after, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding on bothe ſides certaine conditions of peace, the ſame was through the helpe of Archduke <hi>Philip</hi> the king of <hi>Castiles</hi> neuew concluded:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8248:13"/>By which policie, being in very good time put in vſe for the ſtaying of the French ſuccour, which being leauied, was ready to march, it fel out that the remaynder of the French Armies, whom <hi>Gonſalue</hi> ſurpriſed neere the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Garillan,</hi> was quite ouerthrown and as it were vtterly rooted out: So as the French, beeing by this meanes cleane expelled out of the Realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> it was an eaſie matter for the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> there at their pleaſure to build Forts and Caſtles, and the ſame to fortefie with ſtrong Garriſons, and ſo to eſtabliſh a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious ſeat, from whence they might afterwarde eaſely commaund ouer the reſt of all <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the ſame time alſo the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> hauing by his aucthoritie made partition of the <hi>Indies</hi> between the <hi>Porting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les</hi> and the <hi>Castillians,</hi> and by meanes thereof, as it had beene by ſome heauenly decree, they had with vnſpeakable cruelty ranſacked and waſted an incredible extent of Land, and ſo ſubdued to their gouernment all <hi>America,</hi> togeather with that great
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8248:13"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of the weſt <hi>Indies:</hi> alſo that at the ſame tyme they had ioyned to their Dominion that parte of <hi>Gaule</hi> which is called <hi>Belgica,</hi> by meanes of aliance contracted by the mariage of the ſayde <hi>Archduke Philips:</hi> thinking them ſelues furniſhed with a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and fit treaſure for the conduct of the warres, as well by reaſon of the Golde and ſpice, which yearely they brought verye plentifully out of the <hi>Indies,</hi> as alſo through the great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that dayly did ariſe of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie nauigations and tranfique of the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Marchants in <hi>Spaine,</hi> (a matter of great encreaſe vnto their reuenues and ordinarie cuſtomes) they caſt in their mindes no longer to forbeare the inuaſion and ſubduing of the reſt of <hi>Italy:</hi> according to which deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, vnder pretence to ayde the <hi>Sforces</hi> againſt the French, they firſte entred into <hi>Lombardia,</hi> a very ritch and fruitfull countrie: There hauing firſt expelled the French, and then ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and oppreſſed the <hi>Sforces,</hi> they ſtrengthened it to their owne vſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8248:14"/>with fortreſſes and ſtrong Garriſons. They altred alſo the eſtate of <hi>Florence, Siene, Piſe,</hi> and all <hi>Thuſcane,</hi> in giuing them ſuch a Duke as they knew to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pend of them ſelues, and in all things to ſauour their attempts: and hauing confirmed the aucthority of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes</hi> in the city of <hi>Genes</hi> (which beeing a verye commodious Hauen, was at that time moleſted with ciuil diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) they aſſured &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it to their owne deuotions.</p>
            <p>Finally vnder the fauour of the prouinces of the Lowe Countries, finding oportunity (after that <hi>Charles</hi> was by the voyce of the electors cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen emperor) &amp; making way through the ſayde prouinces, they did diuerſly moleſt the realme of <hi>France:</hi> Alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of eſtabliſhing the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh religion, they gaue a notable gird euen into the bowels of <hi>Germany,</hi> yea and that with ſo good ſucceſſe, that hauing ouercomen, and in battail ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the proteſtant princes, they bent their whole minds aſſuredly to bring the ſame into ſubiection and ſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8248:14"/>it to their own inheritance, &amp; to that intent placed their ſpaniſh gariſons in ſundry Fortes, euen in the centre thereof.</p>
            <p>Howbeit ſeeing that the naturall moderation and equitye of <hi>Charles</hi> coulde not be alured to ſatisfie their ſo ambitious interpriſes: Alſo conſidering that they were not long able to defend &amp; keepe the places where their garriſons were lodged, as well for that they were to far from <hi>Spaine,</hi> as alſo becauſe they were inuyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſuch warlicke people and nations: And with all ſeeing them ſelues by Duke <hi>Maurice</hi> his armies expelled and ſo dryuen oute of all high <hi>Germany:</hi> beſides that, not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch ſucceſſe as they hoped for in the wars which ſundry times they had renewed againſt the French: bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonderfullye chaſed and much bewayling the taking of ſo notable and ritche a praye oute of theire handes, they did of necesſitye ſtay the courſe of their purpoſes, and ſo proceeded no further in the purſuite
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8248:15"/>of their enterprize: Thus refrayned they them ſelues vntill ſuch tyme as the Emperour, being returned into <hi>Spaine,</hi> the ambitious, haughty and meere Spaniſh mind of King <hi>Philip,</hi> was found meete to ſatisfie their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and that thereby they tooke fit occaſion to reenter, althogh an other way, into that path which before they were forced to forſake: For they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that they could not ſafely at their pleaſures conduct any army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Germany:</hi> Alſo that if they brought any, yet ſhoulde they want both munition and all other meanes wherewith to proſecute the warres, euen the firſt day, vnleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had poſſesſion of the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all had eſtabliſhed good and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Spaniſh garriſons, throughout the Prouinces of the low Countries: that they had rayſed new tributes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtes for their payes: To be briefe, that they had choſen a conuenient ſeate from whence they might at eaſe continue and proſecute the war: But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8248:15"/>perceiuing that they coulde not well compaſſe any of all theſe pointes ſo long as the priuiledges of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie (which doth exclude all ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the adminiſtration of their eſtate, and admitteth no other then home born parſons therein) continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in force: Alſo that they might not leauy any ſubſidy or new tribute: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put Garriſon in any place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the counſell of the eſtates, they concluded among them ſelues, before they proſecuted the inlarging of their limites, that neceſſarily they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne and brydle this the ouer large liberty of the eſtates of the Country, and depriue them of their priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, freedomes and ancient cuſtomes: To be breefe, that they muſt debarre them from all ſuch meanes, help, and ſuccour, as time out of minde had ſtoode them in ſteade, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the dignity and aſſuraunce of thoſe Prouinces: to the ende that thus wreſting and getting into their owne hands the commoditie to erect Caſtles &amp; fortreſſes at their pleaſures,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8248:16"/>and to leauy new tributes &amp; taxes as they liſte: alſo to choſe within theſe floriſhing prouinces ſuch a ſeate as in their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s might ſeem moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dious for the wars, &amp; ſo the whole be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing throghly brought vnder their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection and by ſpaniſh legions aſſured vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they might in time to come vſe the ſame for the aſſaulting of any who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer they liſted. To this ende haue they euer ſince directed their whole ſtudies, counſailes and actions, namely, either by hooke or crooke to find means to diſtribute in the prouin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries a gariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ten thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſouldiers of the old bands: to the end that ioining therto the choice of the footmen of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tors</hi> &amp; <hi>Hencult,</hi> &amp; ſtrengthning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ordinary bands, whome the king according to the maner of the ancient Lords of the ſayd countries, doth vſually intertain, hauing alſo the frendſhip or aliance of ſome <hi>Germain</hi> prince, euen by oth bounde vnto them, or if posſibly it might bee, getting the poſſesſion of ſome neighbour city of <hi>Germany,</hi> they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8248:16"/>may ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ſerue, reen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the ſaid power with a good nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Germayn</hi> horſemen, &amp; ſo vpon euery occurrence haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleat army<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy. For this inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was Duke <hi>Eric</hi> of <hi>Brunſwik</hi> at the firſt choſen, whom the king with an annual pentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reteined: the ſame time alſo took they cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel to take <hi>Coulogue</hi> &amp; <hi>Munster:</hi> but as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtats of the low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trys did obſtinatly refuſe al ſpaniſh gariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; therwith in ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly required the reuoking of thoſe out of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try which yet remained of the french wars, vtterly refuſing (in caſe this were not performed) the aid of money which was required at their hands, it fell out that by reaſon of the ouerthrow taken at <hi>Felbes</hi> in <hi>Affrica,</hi> wherin the ſpaniſh legio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were almoſt quit conſumed, the king, who very vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly bare this dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the hands of the ſtates, &amp; was alredy reſolued to puniſh it as a treazo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being ouercome with the necesſity of his own affaires, ſeemed to find it ſomwhat reaſonable &amp; ſo ſuffered the reuoking of the ſaid bandes out of the countries, to the end with them to keepe and defende
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8248:17"/>the paſſages of <hi>Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaine,</hi> togither with his houlds in <hi>Affrica,</hi> againſt the ordinary incurſions of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urkes</hi> and <hi>Moores:</hi> being neuertheleſſe fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued (as himſelfe could not but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, which alſo the <hi>Spaniaras</hi> in their writings haue teſtified) vpon the firſt commodity to returne the ſaide gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, who with armes &amp; open force ſhould blot out the iniury ſuppoſed to be wrought againſte the <hi>Spanith</hi> name, and with a more ſtricte bonde ſhould bridle and reſtraine the ouer great liberty and authority of al theſe prouinces.</p>
            <p>For the compaſſing thereof, there fel out nothing more fitte and apparant then the Kinges conſtant and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual deſire, care and zeale, earneſtly &amp; ſtrictly to eſtabliſh the <hi>Romish</hi> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the lowe Countries, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him in all his letters written out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ordinarily to accuſe the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the chiefe Lords and Magiſtrates of the country, that they were not earneſt enough in theſe cauſes: ſaying that he well perceaued
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8248:17"/>that vnleſſe they vſed more violent remedies then afore tyme, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh religion woulde ſoone be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed throughout <hi>Flounders,</hi> which for his part, he woulde neuer permit, but rather to hazarde whatſoeuer lands and kingdoms he yet poſſeſſed: Wherefore that he willed and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the rigour of the edicts and placards of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhuld be executed without diſſimulation, and that they ſhould not vpon any, whatſoeuer oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be moderated, qualified or in anye wiſe mitigated: but rather that their ſtrictnes ſhoulde be augmented and increaſed: &amp; to that end that they ſhuld create new Biſhops whom they ſhould make inquiſitours for matters of Faith: that <hi>Granuel</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> a little before become a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, who by reaſon of his intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ambition and inordinate deſire of gouernment, had incurred the malice of al eſtates, ſhould be made head and preſident of that colledge: that to the end the ſayd biſhops might more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently attend to the ſaid inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8248:18"/>ſome of the ſpoiles of diuers Abots &amp; other Prelates of the countrey, whom they accuſed to be to neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting &amp; puniſhing of the heretiks, ſhuld be diſtributed among them: &amp; with al that the hearing of all cauſes, if neuer ſo ſmallye they pertained to matter of religion, ſhould be reſerued to them: whervpon euen at one time, &amp; by one means, al ſorts of people of the ſaid cuntries were greuouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. The princes &amp; great Lords could not patiently ſuffer the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the affaires to be taken from them &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to one <hi>Granuel,</hi> a new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a ſtranger. The nobility coulde not like that authority ouer their liues &amp; goods ſhuld (to the preiudice of their country cuſtomes) be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>known, beggerly &amp; baſe perſons, who coueting their goods &amp; treſurs, might eaſely find means to accuſe &amp; betraye them. The magiſtrates &amp; rulers of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and towns did murmure that the iudgments &amp; priuiledges of the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the kings oth ſo ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nly ſworn, ſhold be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them &amp; put
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8248:18"/>into the hands of raſcals, &amp; ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſids were by oth bound to a forraine prince, the pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready giuen out ſufficient teſtimony &amp; proofe of their cruelty &amp; couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: To be briefe, the whole cominal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty generally complained that in ſtead of ſheepheards they were committed to the cuſtody of rauening wolues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinually gaping after their goods, ſo that ſundry merchants determined to ſeek new habitations in forrain coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, which diuers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did indeed: al theſe things being rehearſed to the king in ſundri ſuplications, peticions, meſſages &amp; ambaſſages (the ſtates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly requiring that by ſuch innouati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo faithfula people to their princes might not be forced any whit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh their accuſtomed obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) ſo far was he fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuing audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their peticions, that contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, obſtinatly refuſing all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, he would that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the decrees of the counſel of <hi>Trident</hi> (whereby in maner al the lawes &amp; cuſtomes of the cuntry were infringed) ſhould be pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed throughout the ſaid prouinces.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8248:19"/>
            <p>And in deede by that meanes hee fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity of the time ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g looked for: For in caſe his preceptes tooke place, the aucthority of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitours once eſtabliſhed, and the lawes and cuſtomes of the countrey infringed, it would be no hard matter to put to death all ſuch as had either aucthority or countenaunce among the people, and ſo alſo the Spaniſhe garriſons together with a new forme of regiment might eaſely be brought in: but contrarywiſe, if herein they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to obeye his decrees (as there was no other likelihood, conſidering how al ſortes of people were by theſe demaundes oppreſſed) then neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt inſue both tumultes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, for the pacifiyng whereof, the Spaniſh garrizons muſt needes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and ſo how ſo euer the world went, the obſtinate reiecting of the Kinges commaundement, ſhould (as a matter of Treaſon) miniſter cauſe ſufficient to chaſtize the people with fire and ſwoorde: Neither was he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in the euent of this counſaile.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8248:19"/>
            <p>For ſome of the chiefe Nobility ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing exhibited a certaine requeſt into the Court, wherein was prooued that the kinges commaundement concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning <hi>Placards</hi> was not onely pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the common wealth, but alſo daungerous to them ſelues, requiring therefore that the publication of the ſayd <hi>Placards</hi> might ceaſe, vntill the king were informed of their dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds by ſuche notable perſons as to that end ſhould expreſly trauail to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: the people thereby conceiuing hope of greater liberty, tooke vppon them, (and peraduenture ſomewhat more then was requiſite) openlye to profeſſe the reformed religion, which the king and <hi>Spaniards</hi> did ſo greatly deteſt and abhor: This ſo honeſt and aparant occaſion miniſtred vnto the king means, firſt to condemne ſuch of the nobility of treazon as had exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the ſayde requeſt, and ſo to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ambaſſadours which by the gouerneſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement went vnto him, &amp; then vnder the conduct of the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> to ſend the old ſpaniſh
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8248:20"/>bandes into the low countries, to the end, vnder pretence of religion, to put to death al ſuch of the chiefe lords &amp; nobles of the country, as coulde not brook their demeanures: to eſtabliſhe paines of death againſt al good men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to entangle the people with charges, impoſtes, &amp; grieuous bondage: to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect fortreſſe &amp; caſtles in their towns and finally to depriue the eſtates and magiſtrats of al aucthority: the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of al dignity &amp; preeminence: the people of their ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; welth: the towns of their lawes, cuſtomes, priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges &amp; freedoms: and finally all the prouinces generally of their auncient honor, dignity &amp; power, &amp; ſo to open a way to the counſell ſo long before taken, for the eſtabliſhing of the ſeate of their premeditated wars in the low countries. Al which things the world knoweth ſo wel: as alſo how the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> hath endeuored to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to effect, that I ſhal not here neede to make any further demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or repe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vndoutedly any man that wold open the eyes of his vnderſtanding &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8248:20"/>narrowly conſider of theſe counſailes &amp; demenures, might plainly perceiue that al theſe drifts tended not to the ſubduing of the lowe countries, who refuſed no kind of obedience, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the laying of a firme founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpaniſh monarchy that they leuel at. And indeed the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> immediatly vpon his ariual in the low cuntries, determined to ſet vpon the City of <hi>Coulogne,</hi> vnder pretence that ſhe had admitted into the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Burgeſes the king of <hi>Spayns</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded rebels, &amp; at the ſame time ſought alſo to bring into his ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ster</hi> in <hi>Westphaly:</hi> both which interpriſes had at one time take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place had not the prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had leuied a ſtrong power in <hi>Germany</hi> interrupted his whol deuiſes &amp; vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubuerted the courſe of his counſel &amp; practiſes: which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, he did not neuertheles forbeare to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand lawes to the inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Coulogne,</hi> or with great threts to moue the magiſtrats to his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: At the ſame time alſo he firſte
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8248:21"/>delt with the biſhop of <hi>Treuers,</hi> (who promiſed al helpe and fauour in the aduancement of the Kings affairs) to the great preiudice of the Palatin ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of hapy memory, &amp; after grew to debate with him for the chiefe town of his countrie, which he affirmed to be vnder the King his maiſters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. He alſo limited to the Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> ſuche counſailours as ſhould no otherwiſe gouerne his Countrey then as if it had wholy ben vnder the abſolute commaunde of the king of <hi>Spayne:</hi> he ſought to binde the Earle of <hi>Embden</hi> vnto him as his vaſſall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of protection and ſafgard: He commaunded the inhabitantes of <hi>Liege,</hi> to furniſh him of weapons, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture &amp; victuals. To be brief, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ccuted vpon al borderers all abſolute authority, commandement &amp; power. And as for the princes that were far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off: firſt he quarrelled with the moſt high and noble Queene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, vnder colour &amp; pretence of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe, and empriſoned ſuch Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh merchants, as vſually trafiqued in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8248:21"/>the ſaid prouinces: he commaunded her to baniſh who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he lift, whiles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not onely harboured and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreated in the low countries ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry lewd perſons, which had beene attainted of treaſon againſt their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, but alſo enriched them with giftes and yearly pentions. By ſundry deuiſes and driftes did they ſolicite the Queene of Scots (being then pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner) to worke ſome new trecherous deuiſe: they loded with honor and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the murderers of the regent of <hi>Scotland,</hi> vſing both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes and endeuours in ſundry their affaires. And what not? they found means by the Popes bul to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Queene of <hi>England</hi> an heretique and vnlawful inheritour: They rayſed troubles againſt her in the hart of her Realme: They put her in daunger of her life: They did by publication ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon her Realme to the firſt that woulde or could ſurpriſe or ſeaze vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, and expreſſely charged <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Auctrich</hi> perticularly, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon the quieting of the lowe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8248:22"/>countries to leauy mortall warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, to marrye the Queene of <hi>Scottes,</hi> and with her to appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to him ſelfe the Realmes of <hi>Englande, Scotlande,</hi> and <hi>Irelande:</hi> Theſe thinges when they coulde not compaſſe to their mindes, by reaſon of the warres reuiued amonge the Eſtates of the lowe Countries, they ſought to bring to paſſe thorough <hi>Irelande,</hi> whether they tranſported, in outwarde ſhewe, in the Popes name, but in trueth by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente, motion and will of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> a number of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> and <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> that they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through that ile, (which they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to finde wholy at their deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) into the realme of <hi>England,</hi> might the more commodiouſly ſubdue and bring it vnder their power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. And had not the King, at the Duke of <hi>Aluaes</hi> perſwaſion (who wondred at the difficulties and lettes that happened in this enterpriſe,) thought it beſt to referre this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8248:22"/>to a more conuenient time, the waight of all this warre had longe ſince bene tranſported into <hi>Englande</hi> in hope that that beeing firſt gotten, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> thereby being at quiet on that ſide of the Sea, might haue a more readye way to ſubdue all the whole lowe countries.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Fraunce,</hi> whiche by reaſon of the Kinges noneage was troubled with domeſticall diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they omitted no manner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, or pollicies, but emploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their whole induſtry, care and ſtudy to wrappe and entangle it more and more in ciuill warres, to the end, that when the ſame ſo floriſhing, and mighty a Realme were with her own weapons almoſte ſubuerted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, they might as their leaſure, with more opportunitye, and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time ſerued, with the leſſe a do ſubdue it: neither neede I here much to ſtande vppon thoſe meanes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they haue vſed to heape more coales vpon theſe ciuil flames: what helpes they haue miniſtered to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8248:23"/>nouriſhing of theſe diſcordes, with what affection they haue trauailed in it, what actions among parties, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinges, leagues and conſpiracies they haue inuented wherwith to maintein and vpholde this miſerable kindling: For the moſt Chriſtian king doth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently &amp; wel know that diuers times they haue procured his ſubiects to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, and ſought means again to bring them to take armes: yea and leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhould thinke they did it for zeale to their Catholique religion, they haue with promiſes of greate ſummes of ready monie ſought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the heartes of the Princes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the reformed religion: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he ignorant how often he hath ben informed that ſundry times they haue endeuoured to corrupt, ſeduce, and winne from their ſworne allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce the particuler gouernours of townes, fortreſſes, and hauens on the ſea coſtes: how they haue with great diligence laboured euen the King of <hi>Nauai,</hi> promiſing him great ſummes of money in caſe he would break the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8248:23"/>peace laſt concluded: yea howe they haue proceeded euen to his highnes, perſwading him to take armes, to the ſubuerſion of the King his brother, and the deſolation of his whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: whome when they perceyued nothing prone to ſerue their miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tournes, they haue ſought to make away with poyſon and ſworde, hauing to that ende, hired expreſſe murderers, who ſince haue by law ben executed. I wil not here ſpeake what number of pentioners the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath bounde to his deuotion, not onely in the priuie councel of the King of <hi>France,</hi> but alſo of all other Chriſtian Kinges, Princes and poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, through whom he doth at his pleaſure trouble the eſtates of ſome, procure the riſing of others ſubiects, ouerthrow and ſupplant whatſoeuer counſails are holden againſt him, and to be briefe, make them determine and like of all that he thinketh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to himſelf: This is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and well knowen to all Kinges and Princes, to whoſe detriment theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8248:24"/>thinges are put in practiſe: none dare the while ſpeak any worde of al theſe matters or once open his lips againſt them: ſo greatly are all mens mindes ouertaken with feare and aſtonied at the onely name of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> nation.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of our <hi>Germany?</hi> which being in greater daunger then any other Prouince, yea almoſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſwallowed vp in this monſterous gulfe of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ambition, doth (as in outward ſhew it were ſufficiently war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted) make no account of her own danger, weening that the fire which hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed her neighbors houſes, &amp; is entred euen into her own bowels doth no whit touch her at all: ſo that this Empire, which aforetime was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo valiantly to defend, both her owne liberty and the liberty of al chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, doth now ſeem to be more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly &amp; rechleſſe in preuenting the eſtabliſhing of that yoke that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the whole world, then any other nation. It is euident that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath in <hi>Germany</hi> not onely his pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſioners &amp; priuy whiſprers which re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueale
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8248:24"/>to him al their Princes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, &amp; enterpriſes, but alſo a publike cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailour in the chamber of the empire, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he vnderſtandeth the whole affaires of al the countrie, &amp; determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth al maters as if he wer a prince of the Empire in the degree of the reſt. He hath alſo his place by his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors in al the aſſemblies of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: he carefully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidereth of al that is done in al their diets, he endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to learne all their ſecrets, &amp; hath no leſſe intelligence &amp; notice, the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> electors themſelues: and what may be more vnworthy, or more contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Germain</hi> natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either more dangerous &amp; fit for the ſurpriſing of their liberty, then not to cal any Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall diet: any conuocation in the Empire: any counſayle: any aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of eſtates: yea almoſte execute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny adminiſtration of priuate iuſtice: without the preſence, counſayle, and (as I may almoſte ſay) without the will and commaundenent of the Kinge of <hi>Spaine?</hi> But vnder what pretence? forſooth by reaſon of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8248:25"/>precinct of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> which beeing numbred among the Emperiall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctes, the king of <hi>Spain</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted among the Princes of the Empire. And what is this, moſt Noble Princes, other then a manifeſt moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery and contempt of you, your auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and auncient glory? Yea and wittingly, before your faces, and with your owne conſent, a ſnarling of you in the haulter of Spaniſhe bondage? The emperor <hi>Charles</hi> hauing by force oppreſſed <hi>Germany,</hi> and beeing inuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with his ſpaniſh and Italian le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, called an Emperiall diet at <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge,</hi> as I weene in the yeare 1548: Wherein he declared that in diuers parts of the low countries there were ſundry Townes and prouinces which in olde time were wont to take their lawes and be ſubiect to the Emperial chamber, wherevnto they did ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilye appeale: To be briefe, that they had alwayes beene holden and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the precincts of <hi>Germany,</hi> wherevpon ſundry and many queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and controuerſies did oftentimes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8248:25"/>ariſe, he would therefore, ſaide he, at once both end their quarrels, and doe a great pleaſure to all <hi>Germanie:</hi> and therefore purpoſed to decree, that as well thoſe Prouinces which he had in the nether <hi>Germany,</hi> as alſo the reſt that lay in the <hi>Belgique Gaule,</hi> beeing reduced into an Emperiall precinct, ſhould from thenceforth be reputed, holden, and tearmed, <hi>The precinct of Burgundy:</hi> and that in reſpect therof, he and his ſucceſſors ſhould disburſe towarde the charges of the Empire, twiſe ſo much as euery two Electours were to contribute to the warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turke:</hi> and ſo they ſhould hereafter remaine exempt and free, not onely from all kindes of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and collections of mony, but alſo from al iuriſdiction of the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the lawes and decrees of the Empire. Here may we beholde the price of the ſpoiles of our iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aucthority and power, alſo the rewarde of our bondage: This is that ſmall ſumme of money wherewith the moſte ſacred dignitie and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8248:26"/>of our Empire is ſupplanted, &amp; authority giuen to aforeine prince, (with whom we haue no bond of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, correſpondence of language, neighborhod, or agreement of lawes and cuſtomes) to enter into our diets: to haue a place in our aſſemblies: to giue his voice in our Emperial cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: to be briefe, to peruſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of al our counſailes, and actions, either publike or priuate.</p>
            <p>If to ſerue a maiſter, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he be neither rigorous he hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, be of it ſelfe a miſery, who ſeeth not our Germany in moſte miſerable eſtate, where the King of Spaine may, if he wil, commaunde at pleaſure? But what need I ſay, he might if he would, ſith al the world doth plainly ſee that in effect he doth commande both far and neer? For what is it that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard hath not gained by the erectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this precinct of Burgundy? except that he doth not onely rule there at his pleaſure, but alſo vſeth al abſolute authority ouer the precinct of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaly, which time out of minde was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8248:26"/>accounted one of the chiefeſt, and mightieſt in all Germany: yea he ſo commaundeth there, that there is none which dare in any wiſe controll or gainſay him. As for example. Haue not the inhabit antes of Liedge hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto obeyed his Empire: either the Duchyes of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Iuliers:</hi> and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the whole territories of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne, and Weſtphaly, beene at his deuotion? And yet not content with this kinde of commaundement, he ſeeketh after a newe ſorte of obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſubdue and conquere them, and ſo to extend his Empire general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouer all Germany: Therefore to ſay nothing of thoſe men, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in poſſeſsion almoſte of all the ſtraightes of Germanie, euen from the foote of the Alpes to the Ocean Sea, are moſte readye to obey his commaundementes, and dare not refuſe any of his requeſtes: neither to ſpeake of thoſe who being by bloud, alliance, league, and neere affinity vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and knit vnto him, do commaund ouer Iſtria, Carinthia, Croatia, &amp; the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8248:27"/>moſt part of <hi>Pannonia,</hi> yea and beare ſoueraigne authority euen in <hi>Bauaria,</hi> poſſeſsing all the heades and ſprings of the Riuers of <hi>Licus, Aenus,</hi> and <hi>Danow,</hi> and are pearched ouer the heades of <hi>Augusta, Ratiſpone,</hi> and other mighty Emperial cities: to hold my peace, alſo of thoſe, who holding as it were the rudder of the Empire, (in hope hereafter to attaine to the ſucceſsion of the kingdome of <hi>Spain</hi>) will not once oppoſe them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his riſing and might: who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not whervnto this vnquenchable thirſt &amp; ambition of the young Duke of <hi>Banaria,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Frifinguen</hi> doeth tende? who beeing egged on by the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> induſtrie, armed with his authority, and kindeled with his commaundementes, is ſo inflamed and burneth in ſo wonderfull ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he can not be ſatiſfied with anye Biſhoplike dignities or prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly authorities whatſouer? he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in a moment atteined vnto ſo greate and mightie power, that in ſtrength he may compare with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8248:27"/>Kinges of <hi>Europe,</hi> and is iuſtly to be doubted of, and feared among all the Princes of <hi>Germany:</hi> And in truth there be ſundry noble Realmes in <hi>Europe,</hi> which neither in greateneſſe and extent: in multitude of people: in ſtrength of ſouldiers: or in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all thinges neceſſary, are to be compared with the principalities that pertaine to his iuriſdiction and are vnder his obedience: all which notwithſtanding, he can not yet be quiet, but frying and flaming in the ambitious fury of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he coueteth and aſpireth daily to greater matters: For he hath already by the King of <hi>Spains</hi> helpe and ſuite obteined, beſides the Biſhoppricks of <hi>Friſinguen,</hi> and <hi>Hildeſheim,</hi> the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paltye ouer the countrie of <hi>Liedge,</hi> which in ſcituation, extent and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of people is nothing inferiour to any other Prouince: herevnto en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoreth he alſo to ioyne the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip of <hi>Coulogne:</hi> for notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hitherto the Countrey of <hi>Liedge</hi> hath openly enough, and vnfayned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8248:28"/>aided and ſuccoured the Spaniards with armour, artillery, victuals, and al other neceſſarye prouiſion for the warres, yet ſo long as the Biſhop was any whit reſtrained in the awe of the Biſhop of Coulogne, he thought it not good plainly to ſhew his mind, but although in effect he had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his whole eſtate to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh obedience, yet did he ſtill in words beare himſelf a newter: howbe it now to the end the Spaniard might without controlement commaunde at pleaſure hee ſeeketh partely by force, partely by threatninges, and partely by the Popes aucthoritie to inueſt him (or rather in his name and perſon him ſelfe) with the electorall dignitie, and Archebiſhoppricke of Coulogne, by whoſe meanes he may not onely proſecute his wars in the lowe countries, and nether Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, euen with the weapons and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Germanie it ſelfe: but alſo prepare the waye to ſubdue to his dominions all the vpper Germany
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8248:28"/>alſo, and take into his handes the diſpoſition of the toules and tributes due to the Electors, and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whiche haue alwayes (moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Princes) beene accounted, and that iuſtly, the ſinewes and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the dignity and aucthority of your Empire: but beeing once loſte, and through this newe electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Archebiſhop of Coulogne, reduced into the power of a forraine Prince will be vnto you in ſteade of fetters and ſtockes, to kepe you from leauying warre in your neceſſities, and to force you to bowe downe your neckes to the Spaniſh yoke, ſo often or whenſoeuer he ſhall thinke good.</p>
            <p>For hereafter ſhall not King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipp</hi> neede to trouble him ſelfe with making a bridge ouer the Rhyne as did <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> ſith the chiefe city of the Empire, the Electoral ſea of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne, &amp; the Archbiſhops whole dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſhal with the twinkling of his eie be as redy to obey him as ther Prince,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8248:29"/>and ſo ſtand him in ſtead of a bridge, gate, and paſſage: what elſe ſhall the <hi>Spaniarde</hi> neede whereby abſolutely to commaunde ouer all <hi>Germany?</hi> to preſcribe lawes, and ordinances at his pleaſure? and to leauy warres againſt whom ſo euer he ſhall thinke good? vnleſſe peraduenture he wanteth yet ſome hauen in the mouth of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> ſea wherby he may vpon euery, neceſsity tranſporte his ſouldiers out of <hi>Spaine:</hi> But for that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, yea ſo well that he can not ſtand in neede of any more: for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of raiſing warre in <hi>Frieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and tranſporting victuals into the lowe Countries, he earneſtly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth poſſeſsion of the riuer of <hi>Ems:</hi> for the atteining whereof, he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen commiſsion to <hi>Billy</hi> the <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale</hi> ſo to deale with <hi>Ertſart</hi> Earle of Eaſt <hi>Friſeland</hi> his vaſſal, that he would as it were in loane and for a tyme graunt him the vſe of the Towne of <hi>Embden:</hi> Offering in recompence and rewarde for ſo greate a benefite, the propriety of the Towne of <hi>Groening,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8248:29"/>(which beeing enuyroned with the ſpaniſh forces, and ſecluded from all commodity of victuals, he may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer when he liſt) alſo the gouernment of <hi>Burgundy</hi> with the reuenues, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, and other the commodities thervnto belonging, retayning neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe his ordinary garriſons in the ſame. If he may obtayn this, then ſhal he get into his power all the principal riuers of <hi>Germany,</hi> namely <hi>Danowe, Rhine, Like, Aene, Meuſe, Moſelle,</hi> and <hi>Ems:</hi> And as by his kindered, alyes &amp; vaſſals he hath all the lande paſſages open vnto him, ſo now ſhall there be no thing by ſea able either to breake his power, or ſlacke the courſe of his enterpriſes. Finally alſo calling to mind the difficulties and lets which the inuincible force of neither <hi>Saxony</hi> miniſtred in the affaires of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Charlemaine:</hi> Alſo remembring how the one onely towne of <hi>Mayden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi> beeing abandoned of all her neighbours and alyes, did neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe keepe footing againſt the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious army of the inuincible Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8248:30"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth his father: ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the courſe of his victories, yea &amp; wholly brake his power, he hath found meanes to miniſter a medicine and prouide a ſalue for this ſoare, to the end there might be no ſtop to let the aduauncement of his Empire in <hi>Germany.</hi> For he hath by his ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours ſo dealt with the Pope and the Emperour, that beſides all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermentes before mentioned, they haue by faithful promiſe bound them ſelues to conferre to the Bauarian, the Byſhoprick of <hi>Maidenborow,</hi> that is to ſay, the whole power of Saxony.</p>
            <p>And for his part, he accompteth it no difference, whether by him ſelfe, or by his deputy, vaſſall, kinſman or confederate wholly affected to the furtherance of his enterpriſes, he get the poſſeſſion of any thing: Beſides that hee is particulerly and aſſuredly perſwaded, that by this biſhop he may haue aucthoritie to commaunde what he pleaſe: All which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, he is not yet content, but to remooue all manner of ſtumbling
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8248:30"/>blocks out of his way he endeuoreth by all diligent meanes and practizes to create him Primate of all Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo to deale, that by his will and onely aucthoritie all eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Prebends and promotions throgh out Germany may be conferred and gyuen to whom he liſt.</p>
            <p>And do you not yet feele (moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Germaine princes) that the king of Spaine (I will not ſay onely ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth earneſtly) but already poſſeſſeth and keepeth in his hands the ſtate of the whole Empire? That it is he who hauing forcibly ſupplanted the lowe countries, ſhal be Lord of al the ports and hauens of the Occean ſea, &amp; the mouthes of all riuers in Germany? That it is he that at his pleaſure ſhal exclude you from all benefite and vſe of trafique: That ſeeketh the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer the riuer <hi>Ems?</hi> That ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth vpon and diſpoſeth all your tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, toules and reuenues? That pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth Lawes and ordinaunces to the inhabitauntes of Cleeue lande, Iuliers, Liedge, and Weſtphalye?
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8248:31"/>that would bring the ſtate of <hi>Coulogne</hi> to his obedience? that it is he whoſe Kinſmen confederates and reteyners doe commaunde ouer great nations and large prouinces in <hi>Germany?</hi> that it is he who perſonally being in <hi>Spain,</hi> hath neuertheleſſe his ſeat and voyce in all your aſſemblyes and imperiall dyets? that it is he that ſpieth, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth of and noteth all your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſails, actions and moſt ſecret affaires? that it is he that doth not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, forbid, eſtabliſh, and confirme what ſo euer he liſteth, but alſo giueth &amp; appointeth vnto you the biſhops of <hi>Triſinghem Heldeſheim</hi> &amp; that eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth princes &amp; electours of the Empire at <hi>Coulogne, Liege,</hi> &amp; <hi>Maydenburg?</hi> and to be briefe, that it is he who ſeeking dominion ouer the mighty eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſtate of our nation, nominateth a Primate in <hi>Germany</hi> at his deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? and to ſupply all theſe roomes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth vnto you one only perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, one onely man, and him ſuch a one as is very neare vnto him in bloud, affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and confederacie, and bound vnto
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8248:31"/>him by the law of protection: alſo for a number of benefites receiued at his hand, wholly ſubiect to his ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Yea ſuch a one as he is aſſured, will not ſpeake, doe, or attempt any thing without his will and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. And finally that man who he knoweth will through infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies that he hath with many of the <hi>Germain</hi> princes, kindle ſuch a fire of diuiſion and diſcorde throughout the whole Empyre as can neuer be quenched, but by the vtter ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all <hi>Germany.</hi> For who knoweth not that great and old quarrel that is betweene him and the noble Dukes of the houſe of <hi>Brunſwik</hi> for the title of a thouſand and one villages that he requireth of them, Which vndouted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye he will not forget, ne ſuffer ſo to ſleepe: Or who is ignorant of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious emulation that is between this family of <hi>Bauier</hi> and the County <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> for the preeminence of the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torate of the Empire? Or how they do complaine that it was taken from their name, ſtocke and family? Which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8248:32"/>quarrell if this biſhop (when hee is through your ſilence and at the king of Spaines purſuite growne to ſuch aucthority) doth renewe, as vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he will: how many wofull tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies wil it breed in Germany? what a gap will it open to the ſpaniſh tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and our bondage? and finally what ouerthrowe, ſorowes and deſolation wil it bring vpon our miſerable, foliſh &amp; vnaduiſed country? &amp; yet moſt (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble princes &amp; excellent eſtates of the empire) you do not onely beare with theſe thinges &amp; ſay nothing, but alſo taking your ſound reſt, and careles of all, you are become idle gazers (as it were for pleſure, vpon the ouerthrow &amp; calamities of your next neigbours) yea, notwithſtanding this ſo daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a fier hath burned their houſes almoſt to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; be kindled at your gats, &amp; is euen come ſo neere, as to ſcortch your very beds, yet do you not thinke the matter to touch your ſelues either that it is time for you to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the practiſes of ſo ambitious and haughty a Prince.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:8248:32"/>
            <p>And what is to be ſayde to all other kinges, princes, and eſtates of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom? Euen that the like ſloth and ſlugiſhnes detaineth them euery one: For while the onely low countries do oppoſe them ſelues againſte the king of Spaines tiranny, and doe giue al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kings, princes and chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes time, leaſure, and opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to turne away this bondage, &amp; by their example do ſhew how eaſie a matter it is not only to ſhake, but alſo euen vtterly to vndermine &amp; ſubuert theſe foundations of tiranny, there is none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al that wil once ſeeme to miſlike of a matter of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? But as if purpoſedly each one endeuored to augment &amp; increaſe the ſpanierds power to their own deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, ſitting with their armes a croſſe or leaning on their elbowes they doe permit &amp; ſuffer the low countries (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready waſted and conſumed with the force &amp; long continuance of this war) in ſuch wiſe to quaile &amp; deminiſh, that being at their wits ende, they knowe not what counſayle to take, either
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8248:33"/>what other courſe they may beſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> beeing daunted with his brother the Duke of <hi>Anieowes</hi> raſhe and vnaduiſed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes, gazeth vpon the fier which kindleth farre and neere among his neighbours: thinking him ſelfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture of force ſufficient to keep and defend both him and his eſtate. The Duke of <hi>Anieow</hi> not knowing what to doe, can neither determine nor perceiue what is good for him ſelfe. Others likewiſe, wondering at the Realme of <hi>Portingale</hi> which the the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath newly conquered, do ſit ſtill, as not reſolued what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to take. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the meane time, ouer aweth all the low country with his whole power, and finding none to withſtand him, layeth firme &amp; aſſured foundations of his ſo long coueted Monarchy: So that through the onely terror of his name, ſtrength and power, his fame is blown al ouer, euen into the vttermoſt partes of the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſo in effect he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porpriateth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8248:33"/>to himſelf only, the name of <hi>Vniuerſall,</hi> which aforetime the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopps of Rome haue entituled him withal. Which prediction doeth in trueth (moſt noble Kings, princes and Chriſtian Magiſtrates) threaten vnto you a miſerable bondage, and throgh your negligence promiſeth vnto him a Catholike power, that is to ſay, an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall dominion and tyrannie ouer all nations and prouinces, vnleſſe in time your ſelues doe ſeeke ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> was iuſtly ſuſpected of the Grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becauſe that ſubduing certaine people of Thracia, their neighbours, they feared that he pryed into the liberties of the reſt of all their countries: and therefore the Athenians doubting leſt the fire of ambition that conſumed his bowels would braſt out, and not onely kindle in Grecia, but euen conſume all Aſia, thought it requiſit with the common power and ſtrength of Greece to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and breake his might: neither was their ſuſpition in vaine as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8248:34"/>ſhewed: for notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding king <hi>Philip</hi> being preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by death could not compaſſe and bring to effect the imaginations of his minde, yet did he leaue to his ſonne <hi>Alexander</hi> ſuche a choice number of ſouldiours &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers, that the young man being am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, did through their force and valiancy ſubdue not onely all Greece, but alſo Aſia, Siria, Babilon, Perſia and Aegypt: and hauing ſcoured all ouer euen to the ends of India, and Scithia, did in a ſmall time erect and eſtabliſh the third and chief monarchie of the worlde after the Perſians. All which notwithſtanding, we do not yet feare the ambitious power of the King of Spaine, neither thinke it neceſſary to ſuppres his vnreaſonable forces, who not in one place onely, but in many and diuers, hath his whole armies of olde bandes, and practiſed ſouldiers, whom he ſtill doth mainteine in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary garriſons: &amp; hath ready at all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaies aboue 30000. men of war: who hath exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the limits of his Empire into Affrica, Aſia, Europe, and Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8248:34"/>euen to the Eaſt, and Weſt Indies: who by Sea hath ouerthrown the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Ottomans: who hath ioyned to his kingdom al Portingale with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable other Ilandes, and moſte floriſhing kingdomes: who ruleth Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which was wont to command ouer all the world, as it pleaſe him: who is Lord of ſundry portes and hauens in Affrica: who euery where poſſeſſeth the Ocean Sea: who hath in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the chiefeſt Ilandes and hauens of the mediterranean ſea: &amp; to be briefe who through the only terrour of his name, decreeth, commandeth and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually fulfilleth what he liſt among all Princes and Chriſtian nations.</p>
            <p>Howbeit if any man weene that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. tenting him ſelf with ſo large an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, he will not hereafter atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt any thing but what equity &amp; law ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: vndoutedly the ſame is willingly deceiued, &amp; flattring himſelf, hath no care of his own honor, liberty, or life. For firſt the deſire of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is vn ſatiable, &amp; like to a flaming fire, which the more ſtuf &amp; mater that it findeth,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8248:35"/>the further it doth ſtretch and extend it ſelfe, waſting all as it goeth. Againe who ſeeth not that by this manifeſt vſurping of Portingale, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the face of the whol world, the king of Spaine meaneth not to ſubmit himſelfe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lawes, rytes, or capitulations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. For if he had thought himſelf to haue had any right in the ſayde ſucceſsion, why did he by force pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the lawes? or by fire and ſworde the holy decree of the ludges? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he abuſed King <hi>Antony,</hi> the Queene, mother to the moſt chriſtian King, the Duke of <hi>Bragrance,</hi> &amp; euen the Prince of <hi>Parmats</hi> ſonne: and to be briefe, all thoſe that pretended any title to the ſayd kingdome?</p>
            <p>Shall we then yet thinke that either conſcience, iuſtice, or equitie can take place in him, who ſo euidently hath declared that in matter of gouerment he will not take or meaſure his right, other then with the power and force of his armies? that hee, who with his money hath armed the Turke againſt the Venetians, &amp; ſo turned that ſtorm
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8248:35"/>from himſelfe vnto his confederates in Ciprus, can thinke himſelfe bound vnto any couenants, treaties, or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoeuer? That that mans fierie ambition, who hath not kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny couenants with the inhabitaunts of Grenado, the Indians, or Flemings any longer then he founde them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to himſelfe, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſtayed by any bonde of league or confederacie of aliance? Either what conſcience, right or lawe can binde him, who by the principles or precepts of his religion, together with the Byſhopp of Romes authoritie, thinketh himſelfe releaſed from all bondes of fayth or promiſe? ſhall we hope that he, who coulde not by any bonds of mariage be reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Inceſt: for any loue or duetie of matrimony abſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adultery: for any naturall loue forbeare parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide: or for any ſworne fayth refrayne from periurie: being beſides ſo ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as all men know: ſo deſirous to enlarge the bounds of his Empire, &amp; ſo far tranſported with purſuit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, may by any propoſition of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8248:36"/>right, lawe, or Iuſtice be cooled and brought to reaſonable order in whatſoeuer matter? As if it were not as lawful for the Biſ. of Rome to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe, by his Bul, as wel with the lawes, bounds and limits of kingdomes and Prouinces, as with the bands of matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, and faith ſo ſolemnly ſworne. But to what purpoſe is it for vs to think vnder pretence of law &amp; iuſtice to moderate that mans ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who hath bene long reſolued, that he hath lawfull and iuſt title, to inuade other mens kingdomes, and if he may to bring the ſame into his ſubiection?</p>
            <p>For among all princes, potentates, and Chriſtian common wealthes, who is there againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he thinketh not him ſelfe long ſince to haue had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and iuſt cauſe to moue warres? He will accuſe the King of Fraunce, that he did not onely not hinder his brothers attempts in Flanders, but alſo ayded him with men, money, and Weapons, and ſo beganne the warres: That in the behoofe of the Queen his mother, he hath in warlike
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8248:36"/>maner aſſaulted the Ilandes appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his obedience, fought with his nauie: and not onely receiued &amp; harboured <hi>Don Anthony</hi> his enemy &amp; ſuppoſed rebel in his kingdome, but alſo aided and aſsiſted him both with men and money: alſo that he ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the low countries aſmuch as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could.</p>
            <p>To the Queene of England he will alleage, that firſt by the Popes Bulles ſhe is denounced an heretique, and therevpon excommunicated: then, that in diuerſe dealinges both by Sea and by land ſhe hath ſhewed herſelfe to be his enemie: that in her domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſhe hath harboured and ayded his enemies, with men, munition, money and ſhippes: that ſhe hath fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured <hi>Don Anthony</hi> in all his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes: and that vppon euery oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſhe hath intercepted his nauie and treaſure comming from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</p>
            <p>Amongeſt the Germaine Princes, ſome he wil accuſe for ſuccouring the Prince of Orenge, and others for their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8248:37"/>parſonal preſence in the Flemiſh wars Againſt ſome he wil raiſe controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in reſpect of their territories by means of the Biſhop of Friſenguen, &amp; againſt others for the preeminence of the electorate: &amp; generally he wil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe al to be either heretikes, or to be confederate with thoſe that haue ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Biſhop of Romes obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whome altogether the Pope will (as heretofore he hath done) command to be by force reduced to their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And I pray you, is not al this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſerue for a very good colour to make him, who accounteth of all the Popes precepts, as of heauenly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations: And of his excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as of celeſtiall thunderboltes, to aſſaile them? Who of him ſelfe is a ſworne enemy to religion, abhorring it as the plague of the worlde: who in all his counſailes, purpoſes, practiſes, and leagues that euer he made, hath no other meaning but to roote it out and quight to ſuppreſſe it? and who being the moſt ambitious prince aliue doth yet proteſt that he had rather
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8248:37"/>loſe all his dominions and dignities, then leaue any ſparke of this religion vnque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched? And to be brief, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no more accounte of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, then if they were Turkes, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens or Moores. Yea, will not the Pone thinke himſelfe to haue as full power after his thunderbolts of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, to exhibite Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as a pray to king <hi>Philip,</hi> as had his predeceſſours to giue it to his Father the Emperour <hi>Charles?</hi> Pope <hi>Paule</hi> the thirde and his predeceſſour <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the feuenth did threaten <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth with excommunications, becauſe hee thought it requiſite to pacifie the trouble (ariſing in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many for matter of religion) rather by the aucthoritie of a general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, then by proceedinge by force of armes: yea in the ende with their thonderboltes of excommunication they droue that good prince (for ſtill he relented to them) to ſuch an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, that as an extreame remedie, he was forced to make wars with al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie. And ſhall we now think that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8248:38"/>the Pope do want means to perſwade the king of Spaine (who of himſelfe is ſufficiently inclyned that way) that he hath iuſt cauſe by meere ſtrength to reduce them to the faith of the Romiſhe Church? If any man thinke that the feare hereof toucheth no more but the proteſtant princes, alſo that they which ſtill haue perſeuered in Popery need not doubt or miſtruſt any thing: Let him call to mind that the Henries, Ottoes, Frederickes and other moſt mightye, and in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable vertues, moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors your predeceſſors (moſt noble princes) did in their daies profeſſe the ſame faith &amp; religion with the popes, and yet coulde not eſcape their thon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts and moſt wrongfull excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications: But that ſome of them ſee their Empyres tranſlated and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to forraine princes: Others came bare footed and bare headed to aske them forgyueneſſe, and ſubmitting them ſelues to be troden vnder the Popes feete could not neuertheleſſe mollifie their mindes without ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8248:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>great iniuries &amp; tollerating no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table abuſes: Let him ſuppoſe that the Pope wanteth no occaſions to arme the Spaniard to the deſtruction of the Germaines, ſeeing that they which be of his owne religion, do not onely not oppoſe them ſelues againſt the proteſtantes, but alſo daily enter a legue, amity, and firme alyaunce with them: Let him coniecture that the ſpanierds not beeing able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Germany to their own dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither to reduce it to the Popes obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience, vnleſſe to that end, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract amity with the reſt, eyther in reſpect of ancient allance, or by right of protection, or for feare of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: it is neceſſary for the Germains to ſtande to one of theſe conditions, namely, either to ioyn with the ſpani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes in the conqueſt of their fellow cuntry me, or els vniting their whole forces together, to take armes againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the deliuery of an <hi>Germany</hi> out of their bondage: This vnles they doe ſpedely take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; ſo vſing the oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the affairs of the low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8248:39"/>doe cutte off the encreaſe of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> power, they ſhal hereafter in vain each after other, endeuour to turne away the force of their tyrannie.</p>
            <p>Certainly moſt noble princes, the King of <hi>Spains</hi> power is great: and yet is it ſuch, that as by your ſufferance, (I had almoſt ſaid ſlouth) the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations therof haue ſprong and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen forward, ſo may it again by your vnion as eaſily be ſhaken, and finally with ſmall labour by your power and concorde be brought to vtter ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion. For all the Prouinces of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience do lie ſeparate a great way each from other, whereby their vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals may eaſily be cut off, their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces debarred, and their ſtrength vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ouerthrowen, in caſe you will but of your ſelues helpe your ſelues, and not ſuffer Italy: by a liſt running tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the middeſt of Germany to be ioyned with Flaunders. A matter ſo much the eaſier for you to compaſſe, for that you ſee euidently how al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do abhorre their great tyranny, and attend no other but opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8248:39"/>to free themſelues out of their bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. Neithe are you ignoraunt with how weake a power, and with what a handfull of men, or ſmal beginnings, the Prince of Orenge hath waſted &amp; brought to naught their great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, &amp; conſumed their mighty ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: what a while the low countries (deſtitute of al aide and bereaued of ſuccour) haue borne the brunt of ſo mighty a Prince: alſo in what daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger within theſe fewe yeares <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of Auſtrich, &amp; of late daies the Prince of Parma were of being driuen out of all the ſaid low countries with their whole power: yea &amp; that at that time, had not ſundry prouinces by reaſon of ciuil diſſention departed from the general vnion: &amp; the Duke of Aniow through peruerſe counſail let ſlip his good fortune which he poſſeſſed, they had not only aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doned Flanders, but alſo peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture limited their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions with the Pirinean mountaines. So that as you are not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne their might &amp; ſuffer it thus to growe on, ſo haue you no cauſe moſt noble Princes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8248:40"/>to fear the greatnes therof, or to dant you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valiant defence of your ſelues or reuenge of the common liberty.</p>
            <p>The king of Spains power can not greatly hurt you, if in time you ſee to your buſineſſe: If you neglect not the warres of the low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries: if through your authority you vndermine al Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies purpoſes concerning the riuer of Ems: if you repreſſe the fiery ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Duke of Bauier togeather with his exceeding affection to the king of Spain: if with the moſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> king, if with the right excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Queen of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, &amp; al other chriſtian princes and potentats you do earneſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of ſome neceſſary meanes to ſuppreſſe this their ouer great power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. But if contrariwiſe you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the inhabitauntes of the low cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, your next neighbours (through the ſpaniſh power almoſt waſted) yet to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh of Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many: if you hould your peaces when you ſee the inhabitants of Cleueland, Iuliers, &amp; Coulogn eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quake for fear at the precepts of the king of Spain: if you force not the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of liedge
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8248:40"/>to ayd the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemy with money, munition &amp; wepons, as hitherto they haue ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly don: If you bridle not the vile ambition of the Duke of Bauier, but ſuffer him to ioyne the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of Coulogn &amp; electorial dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to his authority: If you reſtraine him not from ioyning his forces with the ſpaniſh to the deſtruction of Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and exclude not the ſpaniard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the hauens of the Ocean ſea: doubt not but Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders being brought vnder the yoke. Germany deuided into fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: France conſumed in ciuil wars, or with drawn into ſundry opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; diuers affections: the terror of the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh name, &amp; waight of his empire wil become a mighty te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt &amp; ineuitable inundation, which hauing pierſed the cauſies, ditches &amp; ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, wil ſhortly be ſufficient through the fury of his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to incroch al chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togither. Againſt which procedings if any man wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppoſe himſelf, either by force or otherwiſe, he ſhal (though to late) finde that which in the beginning of our diſcourſe wee haue ſet downe,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8248:41"/>namely, that fit opportunitie to doe well being once eſcaped vs (which wil neuer be recouered either by intreaty or compulſion) wil cry vengeaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and bring vppon vs that plague which our rechleſnes and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence doth deſerue.</p>
            <p>This prognoſtication I beſeeche God to turne from all Chriſtendom, eſpecially from Germanie, my ſweete countrie: moſt earneſtly deſiring him in the name of our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST, that he will vouchſafe in his holy ſpirit to aſsiſt all your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſails (moſt noble princes of thempire, &amp; you al other chriſtian Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and magiſtrates) and therewith ſo gouerne, conduct and frame all your enterpriſes and determinations, that you may conclude vpon, and put in execution whatſoeuer ſhal ſeem moſt iuſt, profitable, requiſite, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the benefite of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the glory of his holy name, and the wealth and ſaluation of his people.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8248:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
